Guide to the Sol Stetin Photographs PHOTOS.275
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sol Stetin Photographs
1940s-1980s; undated
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stetin, Sol, 1910-2005
PHOTOS.275
0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box.
Sol Stetin, starting out as a shop steward at a dye shop, rose to become a key figure in the labor movement as president of the Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA). During his tenure as TWUA president, Stetin led the 17-year campaign to organize the J.P. Stevens textile company in the anti-union South; following this, he also engineered the merger between the TWUA and the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union (ACWA) that formed the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) in 1976. Stetin later taught labor studies at William Paterson College and Rutgers University and helped establish the American Labor Museum. The Sol Stetin Photographs Collection includes black and white and color photographs, photocopies of photographs, one contact sheet, and one newspaper clipping from the 1940s to the 1980s that document union events and Sol Stetin's involvement with the TWUA.
Related Archival Materials
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 019); Textile Workers Union of America Scrapbooks (WAG 249).
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in Lozd, Poland, in 1910, Sol Stetin migrated to the United States at the age 10, and later became a key figure in the labor movement as president of the Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA). He began his career in the textile industry and labor unions in 1930 when he took a job at a dye shop and became active in the nationwide textile strike of 1934. He started as a shop steward for the TWUA. Later Stetin became the organizer and director of the TWUA's mid-Atlantic region and served secretary-treasurer on the union's board before becoming TWUA's president in 1972. He continued as its president until its merger with the larger Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union in 1976, which he engineered. During his tenure, Stetin led the 17-year campaign to organize the J.P. Stevens textile company in the anti-union South. He retired in 1982, but continued an active labor-union-related life, helping to establish the American Labor Museum, teaching labor studies and union organizing at William Paterson College and Rutgers University, in New Jersey, where he became the first labor leader in residence. Stetin died on May 24, 2005, from complications of leukemia in St. Louis, Missouri, at the age of 95.
The TWUA was an industrial union of textile workers established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1939. In 1976 it merged with the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU). As a leading organization in the CIO's "Operation Dixie," it led numerous organizing campaigns in the union-resistant South, aiming to help textile workers achieve higher wages, health insurance and other benefits, and to ensure fair labor practices. The TWUA was able to organize new plants and revive some moribund organizations, but it was unable to achieve a breakthrough win which would organize the whole industry. In 1995, the TWUA's textile locals became part of UNITE/HERE, a manufacturing and hospitality workers union.
Scope and Contents
The Sol Stetin Photographs Collection includes black and white and color photographs, photocopies of photographs, one contact sheet, and one newspaper clipping of Textile Workers of America Union events. Some photographs have accompanying correspondence that helps to identify them. Most of the materials are undated but range from the 1940s to the 1980s. The collection documents meetings, conferences, conventions, charity events, strikes, marches, and contains portraits of Sol Stetin and other members of the union. There are also photographs of Stetin with President Lyndon Baines Johnson, then-Senator Herbert Humphrey, Sidney Hillman, and comedian Jerry Lewis.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance is unknown, but collection was likely donated in 2005. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2012.068 and NPA.2009.029.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series by subject and formats.
Series I: Sol Stetin Photographs.
Correspondence.; Strikes and lockouts |x Textile industry |z United States.; Textile workers |x Labor unions.; Clothing workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Clothing workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Clothing workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Clothing workers |z United States.; Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Contact sheets.; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Textile Workers Union of America; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946.; Rieve, Emil, 1892-1975.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973
- Conferences and Conventions., 1939; 1952; 1977; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Contact Sheet., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Meetings and Group Shots I., 1940s-1970s; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Meetings and Group Shots II., 1950s-1980s; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Meetings and Group Shots III., 1940s-1970s; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clipping., May 18, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Other Events., 1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photocopies., 1970s; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Portraits - Other., 1947; 1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Portraits - Sol Stetin., 1948;1950; 1951; 1977; 1978; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Strikes and Marches., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)